[Music]
okay so I'm pretty sure that mmm what
I'm going to talk about is going to piss
off some people and I'm pretty sure that
[Music]
what I'm gonna say is going to be
slightly controversial and I'm going to
talk about somebody who is very divisive
it seems in the popular discourse these
days and I'm going to make my claim that
there is a somewhat of a witch hunt
going on right now which is truly
deplorable this summer I got acquainted
with the thinker by the name of Jordan
Peterson so I want to talk about the
Peterson cult and yes he's a genuine
cult figure but he's also a serious
thinker which is something that people
when they become media stars or get
instrumentalized by various shady groups
forget he's Canadian and he's from the
northern Alberta he's sort of a
gentleman cowboy type he's also a
Harvard psychologist and he wrote a book
called maps and minion in 1999 and
recently he's been accused of thought
crime the people who are accusing in
them I would say that none of them have
actually read his books they've seen
short videos ten minutes long five
minutes long they've seen various
attacks on him various memes you know
and most of his critics
I think misunderstand him
some kind of way so I would like to set
the record straight so his book maps and
meanings is a very rich complex
important book I would say it's a book
that's written in blood so to speak it's
it's that's what Nietzsche and Nietzsche
swards it's it has the real power it has
real power in it and it has the power of
an individual grappling in a deep and
sincere way with with the truth
it's not easy reading and actually its
complexity kind of surprised me because
Peterson is such a fluid talker but the
book isn't fluid at all there seems to
be a very big gap between his let's say
a serious work as a writer and a
psychologist and his public persona as a
kind of free speech advocate and for
some weird reason he's associated with
the right anyway it's very strange to me
that someone with his obvious gravitas
as a thinker would become such a star
first of all and also that also be not
discussed in the mainstream media except
through rather insulting caricatures
usually he's called a neo-nazi which is
the best kind of unimaginative
ideological insult that anybody seems to
be able to come up with you know that's
the way it is these days and these
strange times if you can't fit somebody
into your nice ideological box or if
somebody is too forthright
straightforward not obscure and jargon
rid and enough you kind of ignore them
or you demonize them or you call them
inflammatory names like nah
see or other such that's nonsense and so
peterson is not a nazi or a neo-nazi and
he's not even really right-wing in my
view he seems to me to be a very deeply
compassionate and intelligent
tender-hearted person he's closer to a
sort of george orwell he's a critic
critique of ideology and totalitarianism
and political correctness and all of
that twenty years ago he would be
something left of center although he is
a economic liberal which of course is a
great sin for for the left and i'm not
gonna comment on that because I'm not an
economist but I know there are some
reasons for his mischaracterizations and
that he's got himself into it somewhat
and regardless of what but we're I want
to say that regardless of whatever
political label you put on him I believe
he's somebody on fire with a real
message or something you know genuinely
mmm spiritual and in the old-fashioned
sense of the word he's on fire with the
holy spirit since I'm interested in
religion and metaphysics of all kinds I
have no problem with with that though of
course it's it's taboo to to speak in
this way and of course actually speaking
in this way as I'm speaking opens me up
to as I realized today opens me up to a
great deal of potential abuse a
potential sarcasm potential you know
shallow attacks right the kind same kind
of attacks that
that Peterson is subject to daily I mean
no wonder the guy is ill maybe you can
feel the trepidation I have and actually
even talking about him which is strange
because he's quite a moderate individual
you know he's quite old-fashioned he's
quite fatherly there's nothing cruel or
unkind or you know nasty about any of
his discourse so the fact that he's been
called the not-see is just just
appalling and shows us the level at
which you know the discourse has sunk in
our society in our social network world
and I'm not a Peter Sohn Ian Cinco fan
t'k I'm not a Cinco fent not in the
least I'm actually critical of you know
several of his assumptions and confused
about some of his orientations and I
will separate the wheat from the chaff
in this discussion I will try to say you
know what I rejected what I accept in
his thought that shafts or the chaff of
the wheat I'll talk about first and then
I'll say why I appreciate the man okay
so I'm happy that Peterson is speaking
on both sides of the political spectrum
but I'm puzzled why he glosses over any
critique of sort of Ayn Rand
individualism
I am follow his critique of Marxist
utopianism and post-modernism I think
it's fair enough I don't think it's
profound but I think it's fair enough I
wonder why he doesn't critique the free
market or
the kind of liberal ideological
possession to use another one of his
phrases I mean of course free-market
capitalism is also destructive Marxist
Marxist collectivism is equally
destructive and perhaps they are two
sides of the same coin in my view so
obviously we're destroying the earth the
air the water like greedy predators and
this can't be remedied by 19th century
liberalism in my view so I I wonder why
mm-hmm we can't be critical of extreme
liberalism or radical selfishness as
well as being critical of communism or
Rajat radical selflessness right where
the individual doesn't matter at all why
can't we be rid of be critical of both
these wrong views okay so I feel that
his discourse is a bit dated that it
belongs a bit to the 1980s when it comes
to politics I don't think we have to
choose between one wrong view and
another between the good Empire and the
evil one
I think he seems to think we need to
choose science but I want to say perhaps
there's another way and I have been
wondering if Peterson's psychological
ideas are slightly reductive I'm pretty
sure that he's solid from a scientific
point of view and nobody's accusing him
of not being a rigorous of scientist in
fact he quite obviously is a rigorous
scientist but I wonder if the system of
categorization he speaks above the five
year the four big five personality
traits IQ tests etc have a kind of
totalitarian potential somewhat like
5-year plans could such tests be used by
companies to create a nightmarish
meritocracy where everyone was evaluated
by their DNA or their genes or their IQ
or whatever you know could a class of
untouchables arise from people being
left out
the mix I think there is some virtue to
the left which he does actually
acknowledge even as a vociferous
critique of Marxist materialism
dialectics which I am also the virtue of
the left is to expand the net of care
and compassion to the widest group of
people possible and that is a good thing
and finally while I find no evidence of
bigotry in Peterson's thinking I wonder
why is being propped up by people who
are so irrationally opposed to gay
marriage there so ardently I don't get
it I don't get the outright movement I
don't think he's a part of it I think
he's actually critiqued it but I think
he has a lot of fans who are all
apparently all right I think maybe there
are a few things about postmodern
society that are not just satanic right
and evil I think that it's great that
we've been able to extend our protection
to vulnerable people and look outside of
our own tribe and I think perhaps
Peterson might be a bit provincial in
his Christianity which is not so rare
for a Christian certainly or are a
Buddhist or a Muslim either of course so
while Peterson never criticizes gay
marriage I wonder why he doesn't lend
more support to it is he worried about
defending his his more traditional fans
is he in bed with some of the wrong
people despite a kind of good will and
desire to dialogue with everybody and
lastly one of his best articulations
things that I like that he talks about
is sacred speech and this is actually
what inspired me to to start talking to
start doing these kind of podcast things
it's actually the subject of his arch
enemy
the dreaded postmodernist michel
foucault in his last book the courage of
truth who had many faults but came to
some of the same conclusions as speeders
and weirdly enough the sacredness of the
individual who speaks the truth my only
question here is is sacred speech unique
to Christianity has in sacred speech and
the value of the individual soul and
sacred speech existed before
Christianity and cultures like India and
others and well I am sympathetic and I
agree with the idea that we need to as a
culture rediscover the Father in the
belly of the whale our metaphysical
roots we also need to study world
religion not just Christian religion so
those are my Peter Sounion my misgivings
and at the same time I loved a man in
many ways okay what do I love about him
well firstly the deep practicality and
usefulness of his thoughts that's to me
as a kind of genius right I believe he
has a sort of genius for simplicity for
clarity his ideas rise above abstraction
and and move into the real world you
know when he says clean up your room pay
attention don't say things that make you
weak these are not as simple ideas as
they appear they're deeply thought
spiritual Maxim's are words to live by
the primary spiritual practice is just
that it's cleaning up our intimate space
in our mind as well and that is not
simple real meditation is about paying
attention is about orienting ourselves
properly and yes of course we need the
courage to say what is true so I read
Peterson and I go yeah that's right yes
I think that's true and and yes this is
what I need to do you know it's action
so another thing I think he's right
about is the importance of Carl Jung
which people in the let's say Academy
haven't quite grappled with there to
merely intellectual and young is a very
difficult and visceral thinker young is
not going away because I think that much
of what Jung's gift as much of his
genius hasn't yet been discovered and
it's like that with all very great
thinkers they have a sort of endless
bounty they're revealing things to us
through time and Peterson has brought
Carl Jung back to life with a vengeance
and he's made this most complex thinker
accessible and he's he's bringing out
the darker side of Jung Jung's concepts
of the shadow or the collective
unconsciousness or synchronicity are
sort of bottomless in their depth and
interest I was pretty blown away when I
read Peterson's reading list because
these were the same writers I read in my
youth Nietzsche dusty esky Northrop Frye
Robert even Robert prison you know he's
right to say we should read writers who
wound us in some way who traumatized us
who we can never become recover from who
reorient our entire existence I think
for many people Peterson is just that
perhaps were both Canadians so we like
these bleak massive landscapes so we're
Russian novels are set we like Russian
and northern European writers there are
natural allies we are interested in
exploring the dark pathologies of human
nature and but also our sacred potential
duskie ascii is a writer that hasn't
been surpassed in some sense
so is nietzsche you know both writers
with faults also you know as i say i
I believe that Peterson's writing has
some fatal flaws while being great and I
have no problem with that and I have no
problem with loving a writer who had
some fatal flaws and I believe is great
so he's missing some people from his
reading list like real Kay and Blake and
maybe reneging on and George Gurdjieff
and Buddhist like chögyam trungpa but
that's you know that's forgivable he
studies single people in-depth and
rather than casting too wide a net and
yeah I'm really sorry but I don't think
he's anti-feminist I think he's a
critique of a certain kind of
pathological feminism I I'm sure he
supports the civil rights and gains of
women and I think he simply opposed to
the cliched hatred and repression of
them the horrible man you know I suspect
that he's he represents the resurgence
of the kind of male principle which has
been so maligned lately yes I know this
view will make everybody hysterical
because you know it's it's the most
taboo thing in the world right here here
to critique any cut form of feminism
right but you know not all feminism is
pure so the good the strong the rational
the noble man yeah is you know not in
fashion these days you know he's kind of
a dinosaur he's a thing of the past he's
a subject for scorn
so we can just look at the election of
this pussy grabbing president Donald
Trump and see how repressing the good
father or the good man or the dignified
man you know leads to it's sort of
demonic caricature so I think Peterson's
only against this kind of self-defeating
man-hating feminism today's men you know
have a lot of problems you know they're
addicted to porn and video games they
they're losing out to women in education
and work they're filling up the prisons
and the lunatic asylums there they clean
our garbage and our sewage systems they
run the corporate world and who the hell
would want to do that young men are
hungry for Peterson's message of
responsibility they find a lot of
resonance there you know we need men to
manifest the good the true the beautiful
we need to celebrate men and not just
women we need to celebrate women as well
huh complaining about the patriarchy all
day long it's it's tiresome it's it's it
has no force behind it yeah I just think
Peterson wants to present a balanced
picture of the sexes that's all and I
suspect that Peterson's enemies are full
of daddy issues and they have a problem
with capable assertive strong men
okay and asked to the charge that he's
the enemy of vulnerable groups give me a
scrap of evidence of a single hateful
word he's spoken against any transgender
person or any black person or any woman
I haven't found a single one so calling
him a Nazi is his grotesque I I I
believe that he speaks to people with a
kind of respect and he speaks to them as
individuals you know not as groups so
the issue is compelled speech okay hmm
the government should not be able to
tell us what language to use it's a
civil rights issue obviously why can't
people understand that I mean I don't
think that Peterson has a racist bone in
his body I think he actually is an
advocate for immigrants and people who
need a lift up that's the sense I get
and he's actually helped a lot of people
in his self authoring program greatly I
believe he always addresses people as
individuals and that's the way we should
address each other soul to soul person
to person you know enough of this
labeling you know these political labels
you know yeah are we sick of them
already I mean to me he attacks
ideologies right not people and you know
he taxed them sometimes fiercely but
I've never seen him behave in a way that
isn't with a bit of grace and dignity
even in the most grotesque circus
situations even when people are like you
know after his scalp which they seem to
be at the moment
so he's right to say that the remedy for
ideological possession ideological
position is mythology poetics
metaphysics studying religion find the
dead father that swallowed up by the
whale and just to conclude I'm pretty
sure that Peterson's intention was not
to create a youtube cult but he does
have great ambition and one of them is
to rescue the humanities from the
zombie-like administrators you know in
our universities to get people to
rediscover the underlying metaphysics of
their culture to point out the vast
human potential of every single person
and the potential abyssal darkness as
well he never glosses over the dark side
of a person but tells us to look into
the abyss to look at our own monsters
that our own shadows
there's a kind of danger of course of
blind adoration of this sort of paternal
figure of unthinkingly parroting his
ideas of political instrumentalization
by right-wingers but I believe as
thoughts are based on the values of deep
critical thinking deep humanized
humanism and that goes beyond left-right
dualities people with charisma can be
dangerous and yes we should question
their motives but read the book before
you talk to me before you write
grotesque things on my Facebook page
before you attack me in a sarcastic
facile childish manner read the book and
watches his lectures biblical lectures
and his hundreds of hours of teaching on
the dangers of ideology and his maps of
meaning course
so he's not perfect he's wrong about a
lot of things but in the balance I'd say
he's got a somewhat of a saintly quality
and what happens to saintly people
they're called out as being the
corrupters of youth people are putting
up posters in his neighborhood where his
family lives calling him a Nazi it's
it's it's it's unbelievable you know I I
worry for the safety of of his person I
mean there is this mob you know growing
everywhere full of confused ideology so
and I wouldn't be a genuine Peter
Sounion if I didn't dialogue with the
areas of his thinking that that puzzled
me that confused me that that I disagree
with him but whatever
I mean as I was saying I live in France
and I believe that French people still
can disagree without each other two can
sit around a table and drink wine meet
food and and and they they can still
appreciate each other on a sensual level
you know they're not
they're not going to cast someone into
the fire because they don't agree with
their there are politics you know you
know there's still some spectrum of
humanity here which you know I worry
about the American continent continent
and and how people are there or actually
I worry about the whole world so as you
can see I got a little upset today about
this and I stand behind Jordan Peterson
thank you